<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Maiesties speach in this last session of Parliament as neere his very words as could be gathered at the instant. Together with a discourse of the maner of the discouery of this late intended treason, ioyned with the examination of some of the prisoners.</title>
            <title>Speeches. 1605-11-09</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72431</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898403</idno>
  <idno type="VID">135824</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240900680</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 14392</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S1004</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99898403e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72431)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135824)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2067:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Maiesties speach in this last session of Parliament as neere his very words as could be gathered at the instant. Together with a discourse of the maner of the discouery of this late intended treason, ioyned with the examination of some of the prisoners.</title>
                  <title>Speeches. 1605-11-09</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[96] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Robert Barker, printer to the Kings most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1605.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The speech was given 9 Nov. 1605.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-M⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>One of three states partly in different settings. This state has M1r catchword "did". Sheets may be mixed with the other states.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Gunpowder Plot, 1605 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135824:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135824:1"/>
            <p>HIS MAIESTIES SPEACH IN THIS <hi>last Session of Parliament, as</hi> neere his very words as could be gathered at the instant.</p>
            <p>Together with a discourse of the maner of the discouery of this late in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Treason, ioyned with the Examination of some of the prisoners.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Jmprinted at London by Robert</hi> Barker, Printer to the Kings most Excellent Maiestie.</p>
            <p>ANNO 1605.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:135824:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135824:2"/>
            <head>THE PRINTER TO the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing receiued</hi> (gentle Reader) the copie of the Kings last Speach to the Parliament as neere to the life of his owne wordes, as they could bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered; And being about to commit them to the Presse, as I did his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, There is presently comen to my handes a discourse of this late inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded most abhominable Treason a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst his Maiestie and the whole State. And because that a great
<pb facs="tcp:135824:3"/>part of his Maiesties Speach was grounded vpon that fearefull acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, whereof this Discourse doeth make an ample declaration; J haue thought it would not bee vnpleasing vnto thee to ioyne them together in the Presse. And so leauing thee to make thy best vse of both, J bid thee heartily farewell.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:135824:3"/>
            <head>HIS MAIESTIES SPEACH IN THIS <hi>last Session of Parliament, as</hi> neere his very words as could be gathered at the instant.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Lords Spirituall</hi> and Temporall, and you the Knights and Burgesses of this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, It was farre from my thoughts till very lately before my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to this place, that this Subiect should haue beene ministred vnto mee, whereupon I am now to speake. But now it so falleth out, That whereas in the preceding Session of this Parliament, the principall occasion of
<pb facs="tcp:135824:4"/>my Speech was, to thanke and congratulate all you of this House, and in you, all the whole Common-wealth (as being the repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentatiue Body of the State) for your so wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and louing receiuing and embracing of me in that place, which God and Nature by descent of blood, had in his owne time pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for me: So now my subiect is, to speake of a farre greater Thankesgiuing then before I gaue to you, being to a farre greater person, which is to GOD, for the great and miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Deliuery he hath at this time granted to me, and to you all, and consequently to the whole Body of this Estate.</p>
            <p>I must therefore begin with this old and most approoued Sentence of Diuinitie, <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sericordia Dei supra omnia opera eius.</hi> For Almighty God did not furnish so great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to his glory by the Creation of this great World, as hee did by the Redemption of the same. Neither did his Generation of the little world in our old and first ADAM, so much set forth the praises of God in his Iustice and Mercy, as did our Regeneration in the last and second ADAM,</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:135824:4"/>
            <p>And now I must craue a little pardon of you, That since Kings are in the word of GOD it selfe called Gods, as being his Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenans and Vicegerents on earth, and so ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orned and furnished with some sparkles of the Diuinitie; To compare some of the workes of God the great King, towards the whole and generall world, to some of his workes towards me, and this little world of my Dominions, compassed and seuered by the Sea from the rest of the Earth. For as God for the iust punishment of the first great sinnes in the original world, when the sonnes of God went in to the daughters of men, and the cup of their iniquities of all sorts was fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and heaped vp to the full, did by a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall deluge and ouerflowing of waters, bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize the world to a generall destruction, and not to a generall purgation (onely excepted NOAH and his family, who did repent and beleeue the threatnings of Gods iudgment:) So now when the world shall waxe olde as a garment, and that all the impieties and sinnes that can be deuised against both the first and second Table, haue and shall be committed
<pb facs="tcp:135824:5"/>to the full measure; God is to punish the world the second time by Fire, to the generall destruction and not purgation thereof. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though as was done in the former to NOAH and his family by the waters; So shall all we that beleeue be likewise purged, and not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed by the Fire. In the like sort, I say, I may iustly compare these two great &amp; feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full doomes-dayes, wherwith God threatned to destroy mee and all you of this little world that haue interest in me. For although I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, as all mankinde, so chiefly Kings, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the higher places like the high Trees, or stayest Mountaines, and steepest Rockes, are most subiect to the dayly tempests of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable dangers; and I amongst all other Kings haue euer been subiect vnto them, not onely euer since my birth, but euen as I may iustly say, before my birth, and while I was yet in my mothers belly: yet haue I been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to two more speciall and greater dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers then all the rest.</p>
            <p>The first of them, in the Kingdome where I was borne, and passed the first part of my life: And the last of them here, which is the
<pb facs="tcp:135824:5"/>greatest. In the former I should haue beene baptized in blood, and in my destruction not onely the Kingdome wherein I then was, but ye also by your future interest, should haue tasted of my ruine. Yet it pleased God to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer mee, as it were from the very brinke of death, from the point of the dagger, and so to purge me by my thankfull acknowledgement of so great a benefite. But in this, which did so lately fall out, and which was a destruction prepared not for mee alone, but for you all that are here present, and wherein no ranke, age, nor fexe should haue been spared; This was not a crying sinne of blood, as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, but it may well be called a roaring, nay a thundring sinne of Fire and Brimstone, from the which God hath so miraculously deliuered vs all. What I can speake of this, I know not: Nay rather, what can I not speake of it? And therefore I must for horror say with the Poet, <hi>Vox faucibus haeret.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this great and horrible attempt,
<note place="margin">Three miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous euents be to be obserued in the Attempt.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the like was neuer either heard or read, I obserue three wonderfull, or rather miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous euents.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:135824:6"/>
            <p>First,
<note place="margin">1. The crueltie of the Plot.</note> in the crueltie of the Plot it selfe, wherein cannot be enough admired the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible and fearefull crueltie of their Deuice, which was not only for the destruction of my Person, nor of my Wife and Posteritie only, but of the whole Body of the State in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall; wherein should neither haue been spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or distinction made of yong nor of olde, of great nor of small, of man nor of woman: The whole Nobilitie, the whole Reuerend Clergie, Bishops and most part of the good Preachers, the most part of the Knights and Gentrie; yea and if that any in this Societie were fauorers of their Profession, they should all haue gone one way: The whole Iudges of the land, with the most of the Lawyers and the whole Clerkes: And as the wretch him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe that is in the Tower, doth confesse, it was purposely deuised by them, and conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be done in this house; That where the cruell Lawes (as they say) were made against their Religion, both place &amp; persons should all be destroyed and blowen vp at once. And then consider therewithall the cruell fourme of that practise:
<note place="margin">Three waies how mankinde may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to death.</note> for by three different sorts in
<pb facs="tcp:135824:6"/>generall may mankinde be put to death.</p>
            <p>The first, by other men,
<note place="margin">1. By Man.</note> and reasonable creatures, which is least cruell: for then both defence of men against men may be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and likewise who knoweth what pitie God may stirre vp in the hearts of the Actors at the very instant? besides the many wayes and meanes, whereby men may escape in such a present surie.</p>
            <p>And the second way more cruel then that,
<note place="margin">2. By vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> is by <hi>Animal</hi> and vnreasonable creatures: for as they haue lesse pity thē men, so is it a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter horror and more vnnaturall for men to deale with them: But yet with them both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance may auaile, and also some pity may be had, as was in the Lyons, in whose denne <hi>Daniel</hi> was throwen; or that thankfull lyon, that had the Romane slaue in his mercy.
<note place="margin">3. By insen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible things,</note>
            </p>
            <p>But the third, which is most cruell and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull of al, is the destruction by insensible and inanimate things; and amongst them all, the most cruell are the two Elements of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Fire; and of those two the Fire most raging and mercilesse.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">2. The small ground the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spirators had to mooue them.</note> how wonderfull it is when you
<pb facs="tcp:135824:7"/>shall thinke vpon the small, or rather no ground, whereupon the Practisers were enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to inuent this Tragedy. For if these Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spirators had only bene bankrupt persons, or discontented vpon occasion of any disgraces done vnto them; this might haue seemed to haue beene but a worke of reuenge. But for my owne part, as I scarcely euer knew any of them, So cannot they alledge so much as a pretended cause of griefe: And the wretch himselfe in hands doeth confesse, That there was no cause mouing him or them, but meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and only Religion. And specially that chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian men, at least so called, Englishmen, borne within the Countrey, and one of the specials of them my sworne Seruant in an Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble place, should practise the destruction of their King, his Posterity, their Countrey and all: Wherein their following obstinacie is so ioyned to their former malice, as the fellow himselfe that is in hand, cannot be moued to discouer any signes or notes of repentance, except onely that hee doeth not yet stand to auow, that hee repents for not being able to performe his intent.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:135824:7"/>
            <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">3. Miraculous euent, the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerie.</note> the discouery hereof is not a little wonderfull, which would bee thought the more miraculous by you all, if you were aswel acquainted with my naturall disposition, as those are who bee neere about me. For as I euer did hold Suspition to be the sicknes of a Tyrant, so was I so farre vpon the other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, as I rather contemned all aduertise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or apprehensions of practises. And yet now at this time was I so farre contrary to my selfe, as when the Letter was shewed to me by my Secretary, wherein a generall obscure ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertisement was giuen of some dangerous blow at this time, I did vpon the instant inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret &amp; apprehend some darke phrases there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, contrary to the ordinary Grammer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of them, (and in another sort then I am sure any Diuine, or Lawyer in any Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersitie would haue taken them) to be meant by this horrible forme of blowing vs vp all by Powder; And thereupon ordered that search to be made, whereby the matter was discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the man apprehended: where as if I had apprehended or interpreted it to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sort of danger, no worldly prouision or
<pb facs="tcp:135824:8"/>preuention could haue made vs escape our vtter destruction.</p>
            <p>And in that also was there a wonderfull prouidence of God, that when the party him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe was taken, he was but new come out of his house from working, hauing his Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke for kindling ready in his pocket, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with as he confesieth, if hee had been taken but immediatly before when hee was in the House, hee was resolued to haue blowen vp himselfe with his Takers.</p>
            <p>One thing for my owne part haue I cause to thanke GOD in, That if GOD for our sinnes had suffered their wicked intents to haue preuailed, it should neuer haue been spoken nor written in ages succeeding, that I had died ingloriously in an Ale-house, a Stews, or such vile place, but mine end should haue been with the most Honourable and best company, and in that most Honourable and fittest place for a KING to be in, for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the turnes most proper to his Office; And the more haue Wee all cause to thanke and magnifie GOD for this his mercifull De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuery. And specially I for my part, that hee
<pb facs="tcp:135824:8"/>hath giuen mee yet once leaue, whatsoeuer should come of mee hereafter, to assemble you in this Honourable place; And here in this place, where our generall destruction should haue bene, to magnifie and praise him for Our generall deliuery; That I may iustly now say of mine Enemies and yours, as DA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VID doeth often say in the Psalme, <hi>Inciderunt in foueam quam fecerunt.</hi> And since SCIPIO an Ethnick, led onely by the light of Nature, That day when he was accused by the TRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BVNES of the people of ROME for mispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and wasting in his <hi>Punick</hi> warres the Cities Treasure, euen vpon the sudden brake out with that diuersion of them from that matter, calling them to remembrance how that day, was the day of the yeere, wherein God had giuen them so great a victory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst HANNIBAL, and therfore it was fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for them all, leauing other matters, to run to the Temple to praise God for that so great deliuery, which the people did all follow with one applause: How much more cause haue wee that are Christians to bestow this time in this place for Thankes-giuing to God for his
<pb facs="tcp:135824:9"/>great Mercy, though wee had had no other errant of assembling here at this time? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in if I haue spoken more like a Diuine then would seeme to belong to this place, the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it selfe must plead for mine excuse: For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here commed to thanke God for a diume worke of his Mercy, how can I speake of this deliuerance of vs from so hellish a practise, so well as in language of Diuinitie, which is the direct opposite to so damnable an intention? And therefore may I iustly end this purpose, as I did begin it with this Sentence, <hi>The Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God is aboue all his workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It resteth now that I should shortly informe you what is to be done hereafter vpō the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of this horrible &amp; strange accident. As for your part that are my faithfull and louing Subiects of aldegrees, I know that your hearts are so burnt vp with zeale in this errant, and your tongues so ready to vtter your duetifull affections, and your hands &amp; feet so bent to concurre in the execution thereof, (for which as I neede not to spurre you, so can I not but praise you for the same:) As it may very well be possible that the zeale of your hearts shall
<pb facs="tcp:135824:9"/>make some of you in your speaches rashly to blame such as may bee innocent of this at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt; But vpon the other part I wish you to consider, That I would be sory that any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing innocent of this practise, either domesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal or forraine, should receiue blame or harme for the same. For although it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, That it was the onely blind superstition of their errors in Religion, that led them to this desperate deuice; yet doth it not follow, That all professing that <hi>Romish</hi> religion were guilty of the same. For as it is true, That no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sect of heretiques, not excepting <hi>Turke, Iew,</hi> nor <hi>Pagan,</hi> no not euen those of <hi>Calicute,</hi> who adore the deuill, did euer maintaine by the grounds of their Religion, That it was lawfull, or rather meritorious (as the <hi>Romish</hi> Catholicks call it) to murther Princes or peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for quarrel of Religion. And although particular men of all professions of Religion haue been some Theeues, some Murtherers, some Traitors, yet euer when they came to their end and iust punishment, they confessed their fault to be in their nature, &amp; not in their profession, (These <hi>Romish</hi> Catholickes onely
<pb facs="tcp:135824:10"/>excepted:) Yet it is true on the other side, That many honest men blinded peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with some opinions o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Popery, as if they be not sound in the questions of the <hi>Real pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence,</hi> or in the number of the Sacraments, or some such Schoole-question: yet do they ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not know, or at least not beleeue all the true grounds o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Popery, which is in deed <hi>The mysterie of iniquitie.</hi> And therefore do we iust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conresle, that many Papists, especially our sore fathers, laying their onely trust vpon CHRIST and his Merits at their last breath, may be, and often times are saued; detesting in that point, and thinking the cruelty of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritanes worthy of fire, that wil admit no salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to any Papist. I therefore thus doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clnde this point, That as vpon the one part many honest men, seduced with some errors of Popery, may yet remaine good and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Subiects: So vpon the other part, none of those that truly know and beleeue the whole grounds, and Schoole cōclusions of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, can euer proue either good Christians, or faithfull Subiects. And for the part of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine Princes and States, I may so much the
<pb facs="tcp:135824:10"/>more acquite thē, &amp; their Ministers of their knowledge and consent to any such villanie, as I may iustly say, that in that point I better know al Christian Kings by my selfe, That no King nor Prince of honor wil euer abase him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe so much, as to thinke a good thought of so base and dishonorable a Treachery, wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you therfore, that as God hath giuen me an happie Peace and Amitie, with all other Christian Princes my neighbors (as was euen now very grauely told you by my L. Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor) that so you will reuerently iudge and speake of them in this case. And for my part I would wish with those ancient Philosophers, that there were a Christall windowe in my brest, wherein all my people might see the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretest thoughts of my heart, for then might you all see no alteration in my minde for this accident, further then in these two points. The first, Caution &amp; warines in gouernment; to discouer &amp; search out the mysteries of this wickednes as farre as may be: The other, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter due triall, Seueritie of punishment vpon those that shalbe found guilty of so detestable and vnheard of villany. And now in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:135824:11"/>if I haue troubled your eares with an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt speach, vndisgested in any good me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode or order; you haue to consider that an abrupt, and vnaduised speach doeth best be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come in the relation of so abrupt and vnor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly an accident.</p>
            <p>And although I haue ordained the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roguing of this Parliament vntill after Christ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas vpon two necessary respects: whereof the first is, that neither I nor my Councel can haue leisure at this time both to take order for the Apprehension and triall of these Conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratours, and also to wayt vpon the dayly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the Parliament, as the Councell must doe. And the other reason is, the necessitie at this time of diuers of your presences in your Shires that haue Charges and Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments there. For as these wretches thought to haue blowen vp in a maner the whole world of this Island, euery man being now commed vp here, either for publike causes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or else for their owne priuate causes in Law, or otherwise: So these Rebls that now wander through the Countrey, could neuer haue gotten so fit a time of safety in their pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage,
<pb facs="tcp:135824:11"/>or whatsoeuer vnlawful Actions, as now when the Country by the foresaid occasions is in a manner left desolate, and waste vnto them. Besides that, it may bee that I shall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire you at your next Session, to take vpon you the Iudgement of this Crime: For as so extraordinary a Fact deserues extraordinary Iudgement, So can there not I thinke (follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing euen their owne Rule) be a fitter Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for them, thē that they should be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured with the same measure wherewith they thought to measure vs: And that the same place and persons, whom they thought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy, should be the iust auengers of their so vnnaturall a Parricide: Yet not knowing that I wil haue occasion to meet with you my selfe in this place at the beginning of the next Ses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of this Parliament, (because if it had not bin for deliuering of the Articles agreed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the Cōmissioners of the Vnion, which was thought most conuenient to be done in my presence, where both Head &amp; Members of the Parliament were met together, my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence had not otherwise bene requisite here at this time:) I haue therefore thought good
<pb facs="tcp:135824:12"/>for conclusion of this Meeting, to discourse to you somewhat anent the true nature and definition of a Parliament, which I will remit to your memories till your next sitting down, that you may then make vse of it as occasion shall be ministred.</p>
            <p>For albeit it be true, that at the first Session of my first Parliament, which was not long after mine Entry into this Kingdome, It could not become mee to informe you of any thing belonging to Lawe or State heere: (for all knowledge must either bee infused or acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and seeing the former sort thereof is now with Prophecie ceased in the world, it could not be possible for me at my first Entry here, before Experience had taught it me, to be able to vnderstand the particular mysteries of this State:) yet now that I haue reigned almost three yeeres amongst you, and haue beene carefull to obserue those thinges that belong to the office of a King, albeit that Time bee but a short time for experience in others, yet in a King may it be thought a reasonable long time, especially in me, who, although I be but in a manner a new King here, yet haue beene
<pb facs="tcp:135824:12"/>long acquainted with the office of a King in such another Kingdome, as doth neerest of all others agree with the Lawes and customs of this State. Remitting to your consideration to iudge of that which hath been concluded by the Commissioners of the Vnion, wherein I am at this time to signifie vnto you, That as I can beare witnesse to the foresaid Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners, that they haue not agreed nor cōclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded therein any thing, wherin they haue not foreseen as well the weale and commoditie of the one Countrey, as of the other; So can they all beare me record, that I was so farre from pressing them to agree to any thing, which might bring with it any preiudice to this people; as by the contrary I did euer ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monish them, neuer to conclude vpon any such Vnion, as might cary hurt or grudge with it to either of the sayd Nations: for the leauing of any such thing, could not but bee the greatest hinderance that might be to such an Action, which God by the lawes of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had prouided to be in his owne time, and hath now in effect perfected in my Person; to which purpose my Lord Chancellour hath
<pb facs="tcp:135824:13"/>better spoken, then I am able to relate.</p>
            <p>And as to the nature of this high Court of Parliament, It is nothing else but the Kings great Councell, which the King doeth assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble either vpon occasion of interpreting, or abrogating old Lawes, or making of new, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as ill maners shall deserue, or for the publike punishment of notorious euill doers, or the praise and reward of the vertuous and well deseruers; wherein these foure things are to be considered.</p>
            <list>
               <item>First,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> whereof this Court is composed.</item>
               <item>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> what matters are proper for it.</item>
               <item>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> to what end it is ordeined.</item>
               <item>And fourthly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> what are the meanes and wayes whereby this ende should bee brought to passe.</item>
            </list>
            <p>As for the thing it selfe, It is composed of a Head and a Body: The Head is the King, the Body are the members of the Parliament. This Body againe is subdiuided into two parts; The Vpper and Lower House: The Vpper compounded partly of Nobility, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall men, who are heritable Councellors to the high Court of Parliament by the honour
<pb facs="tcp:135824:13"/>of their Creation and Lands: And partly of Bishops, Spirituall men, who are likewise by the vertue of their place and dignitie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours, Life Renters, or <hi>Ad vitam</hi> of this Court. The other House is composed of Knights for the Shire; and Gentry, and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesses for the Townes. But because the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber would be infinite for all the Gentlemen and Burgesses to bee present at euery Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Therfore a certaine number is selected and chosen out of that great Body, seruing onely for that Parliament, where their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons are the representation of that Body.</p>
            <p>Now the matters whereof they are to treat ought therefore to be generall, and rather of such matters as cannot well be perfourmed without the assembling of that general Body, and no more of these generals neither, then necessity shall require: for as <hi>in Corruptissima Republica sunt plurimae leges:</hi> So doeth the life and strength of the Law consist not in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping vp infinite and confused numbers of Lawes, but in the right interpretation and good execution of good &amp; wholsome Lawes. If this be so then, neither is this a place on the
<pb facs="tcp:135824:14"/>one side for euery rash and harebrained fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low to propone newe Lawes of his owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention: nay rather I could wish these busie heads to remember that Law of the Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monians, That whosoeuer came to propone a new Law to the people, behooued publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to present himselfe with a rope about his necke, that in case the Law were not allowed, hee should be hanged therewith. So warie should men be of proponing Nouelties, but most of all not to propone any bitter or sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Lawes, which can produce nothing but grudges and discontentment betweene the Prince and his people: Nor yet is it on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther side a conuenient place for priuate men vnder the colour of generall Lawes, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pone nothing but their own particular gaine, either to the hurt of their priuate neighbours, or to the hurt of the whole State in generall, which many times vnder faire and pleasing Titles, are smoothly passed ouer, and so by stealth procure without consideration, that the priuate meaning of them tendeth to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but either to the wrecke of a particular partie, or else vnder colour of publike bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite
<pb facs="tcp:135824:14"/>to pill the poore people, and serue as it were for a generall Impost vpon them for fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the purses of some priuate persons.</p>
            <p>And as to the end for which the Parliament is ordeined, being only for the aduancement of Gods glory, and the establishment and wealth of the King and his people: It is no place then for particular men to vtter there their priuate conceipts, nor for satisfaction of their curiosities, and least of all to make shew of their eloquence by tyning the time with long studied and eloquent Orations. No, the reuerence of God, their King, &amp; their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey being well setled in their hearts, wil make them ashamed of such toyes, and remember that they are there as sworne Councellors to their King, to giue their best aduise for the furtherance of his Seruice, and the florishing Weale of his Estate.</p>
            <p>And lastly, if you will rightly consider the meanes and wayes how to bring all your la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to a good end, you must remember, That you are here assembled by your lawfull King to giue him your best aduises, in the matters proposed by him vnto you, being of
<pb facs="tcp:135824:15"/>that nature, which I haue already told, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you are grauely to deliberate, and vpon your consciences plainely to determine how farre those things propounded do agree with the weale, both of your King and of your countrey, whose weales cannot be separated. And as for my selfe, the world shal euer beare me witnesse, That I neuer shall propone any thing vnto you, which shall not as well tend to the weale publike, as to any benefite for me: So shall I neuer oppone my selfe to that, which may tend to the good of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, for the which I am ordeined, as I haue often said. And as you are to giue your aduise in such things as shall by your King be proposed: So is it on your part your duties to propone any thing that you can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mature deliberation iudge to be needfull, either for these ends already spoken of, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise for the discouery of any latent euill in the kingdome, which peraduenture may not haue commen to the Kings eare. If this then ought to bee your graue maner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in this place, Men should bee asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to make shew of the quicknesse of their
<pb facs="tcp:135824:15"/>witts here, either in taunting, scoffing, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting the Prince or State in any point, or yet in breaking iests vpon their fellowes, for which the Ordinaries or Alehouses are fitter places, then this Honourable and high Court of Parliament.</p>
            <p>In conclusion then since you are to breake vp, for the reasons I haue already told you, I wish such of you as haue any charges in your Countreys, to hasten you home for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing of the insolencies of these Rebels, and apprehension of their persons, wherein as I heartily pray to the Almighty for your prosperous successe: So doe I not doubt, but we shall shortly heare the good newes of the same; And that you shall haue an happy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, and meeting here to all our comforts.</p>
            <div type="speech__cont.">
               <argument>
                  <p>Here the Lord Chancellor spake touching the proroguing of the Parliament. And hauing done, his Maiestie rose a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and said.</p>
               </argument>
               <pb facs="tcp:135824:16"/>
               <p>Since it pleased God to graunt mee two such notable Deliueries vpon one day of the weeke, which was Tuesday, and likewise one day of the Moneth, which was the fifth; Thereby to teach me, That as it was the same deuill that still persecuted me; So it was one and the same GOD that still mightily deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered me: I thought it therefore not amisse. That the one and twentieth day of Ianuary, which fell to be vpon Tuesday, should be the day of meeting of this next Session of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hoping and assuring my Selfe, that the same GOD, who hath now granted me and you all so notable and gracious a Deliuerie, shall prosper all our affaires at that next Sessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and bring them to an happy conclusion. And now I consider God hath well prouided it that the ending of this Parliament hath bin so long continued; For as for my owne part, I neuer had any other intention, but only to seeke so farre my weale, and prosperitie, as might coniunctly stand with the flourishing State of the whole Common-wealth, as I haue often tolde you: So on the other part I confesse, if I had bene in your places at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning
<pb facs="tcp:135824:16"/>of this Parliament, (which was so soone after mine entry into this Kingdome, wherein yee could not possibly haue so per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect a knowledge of mine inclination, as expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience since hath taught you,) I could not but haue suspected, and mis-interpreted di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers things, In the trying whereof, now I hope, by your experience of my beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour and forme of gouernment, you are well ynough clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and resolued.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:135824:17"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135824:17"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> DISCOVRSE OF THE MANER of the discouery of this late intended Treason, ioyned with the Examination of some of the Prisoners.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is a time when no man ought to keepe silence.</hi> For it hath euer beene helde as a generall rule, and vndoubted Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xime, in all well gouerned Common wealths (whether Christian, and so guided by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine light of Gods word; or Ethnicke, and so led by the glimmering twi-light of Nature) yet howsoeuer their profession was, vpon this ground haue they all agreed, That when either their Religion, their King, or their countrey was in any extreme hazard, no good Countreyman ought then to withhold
<pb facs="tcp:135824:18"/>either his tongue or his hand, according to his calling and facultie, from ayding to repell the iniurie, represse the violence, and auenge the guilt vpon the authors therof. But if euer any people had such an occasion ministred vnto them, It is surely this people now, nay this whole Isle, and all the rest belonging to this great and glorious Monarchy. For if in any heathenish republique, no priuate man could thinke his life more happily and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously bestowed, then in the defence of any one of these three, That is, either <hi>pro Aris, pro Focis,</hi> or <hi>pro Patre patriae;</hi> And that the endangering of any one of these, would at once stirre the whole body of the Common wealth, not any more as diuided members, but as a solide and indiuidual lumpe: How much more ought wee the truely Christian people that inhabite this Vnited and truely happy Isle,
<note place="margin">Insula foru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata.</note> vnder the wings of our gracious and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Monarch? Nay, how infinitely greater cause haue wee to feele &amp; ressent our selues of the smart of that wound, not onely intended and execrated (not consecrated) for the vtter extinguishing of our true Christian professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb facs="tcp:135824:18"/>nor ioyntly therewith onely for the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off of our Head and father Politike, <hi>Sed vt nefas istud &amp; sacrilegiosum parricidium om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus modis absolutum reddi possit?</hi> And that nothing might bee wanting for making this sacrilegious parricide a patterne of mischiefe, and a crime (nay, a mother or storehouse of all crimes) without example, they should haue ioyned the destruction of the body to the head, so as <hi>Grex cum Rege, Arae cum focis, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res cum Penatibus,</hi> should all at one thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clap haue bene sent to heauen together: The King our head, the Queene our fertile mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and those yong &amp; hopeful Oliue plants, not theirs but ours: Our reuerend Clergie, our honourable Nobilitie, the faithfull Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sailors, the graue Iudges, the greatest part of the worthy Knights and Gentry, aswell as of the wisest Burgesses; The whole Clerkes of the Crowne, Counfaile, Signet, Seales, or of any other principall Iudgement seate. All the learned Lawyers, together with an infinite number of the Common people: Nay, their furious rage should not onely haue lighted vpon reasonable and seusible creatures with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:135824:19"/>distinction either of degree, sexe or age; But euen the insensible stockes and stones should not haue bene free of their fury. The hall of Iustice; The house of Parliament; The Church vsed for the Coronation of our Kings; The Monuments of our former Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; The Crowne and other markes of Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie; All the Records, aswell of Parliament, as of euery particular mans right, with a great number of Charters and such like, should all haue beene comprehended vnder that feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Chaos.</hi> And so the earth as it were opened, should haue sent forth of the bottome of the <hi>Stygian</hi> lake such sulphured smoke, furious flames, and fearefull thunder, as should haue by their diabolicall <hi>Domesday</hi> destroyed and defaced, in the twinckling of an eye, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our present liuing Princes and people, but euen our insensible Monuments reserued for future ages. So as not only our selues that are mortal, but the immortall Monuments of our ancient Princes and Nobilitie, that haue bene so preciously preserued from age to age, as the remaining <hi>Trophees</hi> of their eternall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and haue so long triumphed ouer enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:135824:19"/>time, should now haue beene all consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med together; And so not onely we, but the memory of vs and ours, should haue beene thus extinguished in an instant. The true horror therfore of this detestable deuise, hath stirred me vp to bethinke my selfe, wherein I may best discharge my conscience in a cause so generall &amp; common, if it were to bring but one stone to the building, or rather with the Widow one mite to the common boxe. But since to so hatefull and vnheard of inuention, there can be no greater enemy then the selfe, the simple trueth therof being once publikely knowen and diuulged; and that there needs no stronger argument to bring such a Plot in vniuersall detestation, then the certaintie that so monstrous a thing could once be deuised, nay concluded vpon, wrought in, in full readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and within twelue houres of the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: My threefold zeale to those blessings, whereof they would haue so violently made vs all widowes, hath made mee resolue to set downe here the true Narration of that mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strous and vnnaturall intended Tragedy, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing better occasion by the meanes of my ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice
<pb facs="tcp:135824:20"/>and continuall attendance in Court, to know the trueth thereof, then others that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture haue it only by relatiō at the third or fourth hand. So that whereas those worse then <hi>Catilines,</hi> thought to haue extirped vs &amp; our memories; Their infamous memory shal by these meanes remaine to the ende of the world, vpon the one part: And vpon the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Gods great and mercifull deliuerance of his Anoynted and vs all, shall remaine in ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer dying Records. And God graunt that it may bee in Marble tables of Thankefulnesse engrauen in our hearts.</p>
            <p>WHile this Land and whole Monarchie flourished in a most happie and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull PEACE, as well at home as abroad, sustained and conducted by these two maine Pillars of all good Gouernement, PIE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIE and IVSTICE, no forreine grudge, nor inward whispering of discontentment any way appearing; The King being vpon his returne from his hunting exercise at <hi>Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ston,</hi> vpon occasion of the drawing neere of the Parliament time, which had beene twise
<pb facs="tcp:135824:20"/>prorogued already, partly in regard of the season of the yeere, and partly of the Terme; As the windes are euer stillest immediatly before a storme; And as the Sunne blenks of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten hottest to foretell a following showre: So at that time of greatest calme did this se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly hatched thunder begin to cast foorth the first flashes and flaming lightnings of the approching tempest. For the Saturday of the weeke immediatly preceding the Kinges re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, which was vpon a Thursday (being but tenne dayes before the Parliament) The Lord <hi>Mountegle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Letter deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Lord <hi>Mountegle.</hi>
               </note> sonne and heire to the Lord <hi>Morley,</hi> being in his owne lodging readie to goe to supper at seuen of the clocke at night, one of his footmen (whom he had sent of an errand ouer the streete) was met by an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen man of a reasonable tall personage, who deliuered him a Letter, charging him to put it in my Lord his Masters hands: which my Lord no sooner receiued, but that hauing broken it vp, and perceiuing the same to be of an vnknowen &amp; somewhat vnlegible hand, and without either date or subscription; did call one of his men vnto him for helping him
<pb facs="tcp:135824:21"/>to read it. But no sooner did he conceiue the strange contents thereof, although hee was somewhat perplexed what construction to make of it (as whether of a matter of conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, as indeede it was, or whether some foolish deuised Pasquil by some of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to skarre him from his attendance at the Parliament) yet did he as a most dutifull and loyall Subiect, conclude not to conceale it, what euer might come of it. Whereupon, notwithstanding the latenesse and darkenesse of the night in that season of the yere, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently repaired to his Maiesties Palace at <hi>Whitehall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuealed to the Earle of <hi>Sulis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury.</hi>
               </note> and there deliuered the same to the Earle of <hi>Salisbury</hi> his Maiesties principall Secretarie. Whereupon the said Earle of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisbury</hi> hauing read the Letter, and heard the maner of the comming of it to his hands, did greatly encourage and commend my Lord for his discretion, telling him plainely, that whatsoeuer the purpose of the Letter might prooue hereafter, yet did this accident put him in mind of diuers aduertisements hee had receiued from beyond the Seas, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he had acquainted aswell the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe,
<pb facs="tcp:135824:21"/>as diuers of his Priuie Counsellors, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning some businesse the Papists were in, both at home and abroad, making prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for some combination amongst them against this Parliament time,
<note place="margin">Purpose of the Papists for deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering a petition to his Maiesty, to craue toleration of Religion.</note> for enabling them to deliuer at that time to the King some petition for toleration of Religion: which should bee deliuered in some such order and so well backed, as the King should be loth to refuse their requests; like the sturdie beggars crauing almes with one open hand, but cary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a stone in the other, in case of refusall. And therefore did the Earle of <hi>Salisbury</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with the Lord <hi>Mountegle,</hi> that he would in regard of the Kings absence impart the same Letter to some more of his Maiesties Councel; wherof my L. <hi>Mountegle</hi> liked well: only adding this request by way of protesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That whatsoeuer the euent herof might prooue, it should not be imputed to him, as proceeding from too light and too suddaine an apprehension, that hee deliuered this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, being only moued thereunto for demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration of his ready deuotion, and care for preseruation of his Maiestie and the State.
<pb facs="tcp:135824:22"/>And thus did the Earle of <hi>Salisbury</hi> presently acquaint the Lord <hi>Chamberlaine</hi> with the said Letter.
<note place="margin">The Lord <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine</hi> made priuie to the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by the Earle of <hi>Salisbury.</hi>
               </note> Whereupon they two in presence of the Lord <hi>Mountegle,</hi> calling to minde the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer intelligence already mentioned, which seemed to haue some relatiō with this Letter: The tender carewhich they euer caried to the preseruation of his Maiesties Person, made them apprehend, that some perillous attempt did thereby appeare to bee intended against the same, which did the more neerely cōcerne the said Lord Chamberlain to haue a care of, in regard that it doth belong to the charge of his Office to ouersee as well all places of As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly where his Maiesty is to repaire, as his Highnesse owne priuate Houses. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did the sayd two Counsailors conclude, That they should ioine vnto themselues three more of the Councell, to wit, the Lord Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, the Earles of <hi>Worcester</hi> and <hi>Northampton</hi> to bee also particularly acquainted with this accident, who hauing all of them concurred together to the reexamination of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the sayd Letter, they did conclude, That how slight a matter it might at the first
<pb facs="tcp:135824:22"/>appeare to be, yet was it not absolutely to be contemned, in respect of the care which it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooued them to haue of the preseruation of his Maiesties person:
<note place="margin">Thought meete by the Counsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours to acquaint the King with the Letter.</note> But yet resolued for two reasons, first to acquaint the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe with the same before they proceeded to any further Inquisition in the matter, aswell for the expectation and experience they had of his Maiesties fortunate Iudgement in clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and soluing of obscure riddles &amp; doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mysteries; as also because the more time would in the meane while be giuen for the Practise to ripen, if any was, whereby the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery might be the more cleere &amp; euident, and the ground of proceeding thereupon more safe, iust, and easie. And so according to their determination did the sayd Earle of <hi>Salisbury</hi> repaire to the King in his Gallery vpon Friday, being <hi>Alhallow</hi> day,
<note place="margin">Vpon Allhallow day the Earle of <hi>Salisbury</hi> shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Letter to the King.</note> in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoone, which was the day after his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties arriual, and none but himselfe being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent with his Highnesse at that time, where without any other speech or iudgement gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the Letter, but onely relating simply the forme of the deliuery thereof, he presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:135824:23"/>it to his Maiestie. The contents where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of follow.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>MY Lord, Out of the loue I beare to some of your friends, I haue a care of your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation. Therefore I would aduise you, as you tender your life, to deuise some excuse to shift off your attendance at this Parliament. For God and man haue concurred to punish the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednesse of this Time. And thinke not slightly of this Aduertisement, but retire your selfe into your Countrey, where you may expect the euent in safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. For though there be no apparance of any stirre, yet I say, they shall receiue a terrible Blow this Parliament, and yet they shall not see who hurts them. This counsell is not to be contemned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it may doe you good, and can doe you no harme; for the danger is past so soone as you haue burnt the Letter. And I hope God will giue you the grace to make good vse of it: To whose holy protection I commend you.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>The King no sooner read the Letter, but after a little pause,
<note place="margin">His Maiesties iudgement of the Letter.</note> and then reading it ouer againe, hee deliuered his iudgement of it in
<pb facs="tcp:135824:23"/>such sort, as he thought it was not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, for that the Style of it seemed to be more quicke and pithie, then is vsuall to be in any Pasquil or Libell (the superfluities of idle braines:) But the Earle of <hi>Salisbury</hi> perceiuing the King to apprehēed it deeplier then he loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for, knowing his Nature, told him that he thought by one sentence in it, that it was like to be written by some foole or mad man, reading to him this Sentence in it, <hi>For the danger is past as soone as you haue burnt the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> which hee said, was likely to be the say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a foole: for if the danger was past so soone as the Letter was burnt, then the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning behoued to be of little auaile, when the burning of the Letter might make the danger to be eschewed. But the King by the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry considering the former Sentence in the Letter, <hi>That they should receiue a terrible Blow at this Parliament, and yet should not see who hurt them,</hi> Ioyning it to the sentence imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly following, already alledged, did there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon coniecture, That the danger mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, should bee some suddaine danger by blowing vp of Powder: For no other Insur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,
<pb facs="tcp:135824:24"/>Rebellion, or whatsoeuer other pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate and desperate Attempt could bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted or attempted in time of Parliament, and the Authors therof vnseene, except only if it were by a blowing vp of powder, which might bee performed by one base knaue in a darke corner; whereupon he was mooued to interprete and construe the latter Sentence in the letter (alledged by the Earle of <hi>Salisbury</hi>) against all ordinary sense and construction in Grammar, as if by these words, <hi>For the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is past as soone as you haue burned the Letter,</hi> should be closely vnderstood the suddaintie and quicknesse of the danger, which should bee as quickly perfourmed and at an end, as that paper should bee of bleasing vp in the fire; turning that word of <hi>as soone,</hi> to the sense of,
<note place="margin">His Maiesties opinion for fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der roomes of the Parliament house.</note>
               <hi>as quickly.</hi> And therfore wished, that before his going to the Parliament, the vnder roumes of the Parliament house might bee well and narrowly searched. But the Earle of <hi>Salisbury</hi> woondering at this his Maiesties Commentary, which he knew to be so farre contrary to his ordinary and naturall dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, who did rather euer sinne vpon the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:135824:24"/>side, in not apprehending nor trusting due Aduertisements of Practises and Perils when he was truely enformed of them, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he had many times drawen himselfe into many desperate dangers: and interpreting rightly this extraordinarie Caution at this time to proceed from the vigilant care hee had of the whole State, more then of his owne Person, which could not but haue all perished together, if this designement had succeeded: Hee thought good to dissemble still vnto the King, that there had beene any iust cause of such apprehension: And ending the purpose with some merry iest vpon this Subiect, as his custome is, tooke his leaue for that time. But though he seemed so to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect it to his Maiestie; yet his customable and watchfull care of the King and the State still boyling within him, And hauing with the blessed Virgine <hi>Mary</hi> layd vp in his heart the Kings so strange iudgement and constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it; Hee could not be at rest till hee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted the foresaid Lords what had passed betweene the King &amp; him in priuat. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they were also earnest to renew againe
<pb facs="tcp:135824:25"/>the memory of the same purpose to his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, as it was agreed that he should the next day, being Saturday, repaire to his Highnes: which he did in the same priuie Gallery, and renewed the memory thereof, the L. <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine</hi> then being present with the King.
<note place="margin">The determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to search the Parliament house and the roomes vnder it.</note> At what time it was determined, that the sayd Lord <hi>Chamberlaine</hi> should, according to his custome and Office, view all the Parliament Houses, both aboue and below, and consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what likelihood or appearance of any such danger might possibly be gathered by the sight of them: But yet, aswell for staying of idle rumors, as for being the more able to discerne any mysterie, the nearer that things were in readinesse, his iourney thither was ordeined to bee deferred till the afternoone before the sitting downe of the Parliament, which was vpon the Munday following. At what time hee (according to this conclusion) went to the Parliament house accompanied with my Lord <hi>Mountegle,</hi> being in zeale to the Kings seruice earnest and curious to see the euent of that accident whereof hee had the fortune to be the first discouerer: where, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:135824:25"/>viewed all the lower roumes, hee found in the vault vnder the vpper House great store and prouision of Billets,
<note place="margin">Wood and Cole found by the L. <hi>Chamberlaine</hi> in the Vault.</note> Faggots and Coales: And enquiring of <hi>Whyneard</hi> keeper of the Wardrobe, to what vse hee had put those lower roumes and cellars; he told him, That <hi>Thomas Percy</hi> had hired both the house and part of the Cellar or Vault vnder the same, and that the Wood and Coale therein was the sayde Gentlemans owne prouision. Whereupon the Lord <hi>Chamberlaine,</hi> casting his eye aside, perceiued a fellow standing in a corner there, calling himselfe the said <hi>Percyes</hi> man, and keeper of that house for him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Guido Fawks</hi> bearing the name of <hi>Percies</hi> man.</note> but indeed was <hi>Guido Fawkes,</hi> the owner of that hand which should haue acted that mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strous Tragedie.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Chamberlaine</hi> looking vpon all things with a heedful indeed, yet in outward appearance with but a carelesse and racklesse eye (as became so wise and diligent a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster) hee presently addressed himselfe to the King in the said priuie Gallerie, where in the presence of the Lord <hi>Treasurer,</hi> the Lord <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall,</hi> the Earles of <hi>Worcester, Northampton,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:135824:26"/>and <hi>Salisbury</hi> he made his report,
<note place="margin">The Lord <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine</hi> report and iudgement of what he had obserued in the search.</note> what hee had seene and obserued there; noting that <hi>Mountegle</hi> had told him, That he no sooner heard <hi>Thomas Percy</hi> named to be the posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sour of that house, but considering both his backwardnes in Religion, and the old deare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in friendship betweene himselfe and the sayd <hi>Percy,</hi> hee did greatly suspect the matter, &amp; that the Letter should come from him. The said Lord <hi>Chamberlaine</hi> also tolde, That he did not wonder a little at the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie great prouision of wood and coale in that house, where <hi>Thomas Percy</hi> had so seldome occasion to remaine; As likewise it gaue him in his minde that his man looked like a very tall and desperate fellow.</p>
            <p>This could not but encrease the Kings former apprehension and iealousie: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon hee insisted (as before) that the House was narrowly to be searched, and that those Billets and Coales would be searched to the bottome, it being most suspicious that they were layd there onely for couering of the powder. Of this same minde also were all the Counsailors then present. But vpon the
<pb facs="tcp:135824:26"/>fashion of making of the search was it long debated:
<note place="margin">Disputation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the maner of the further search.</note> For vpon the one side they were all so iealous of the Kings safetie, that they all agreed, that there could not be too much caution vsed for preuenting his danger. And yet vpon the other part they were al extreme loth &amp; daintie, that in case this Letter should prooue to be nothing but the euaporation of an idle braine; then a curious search being made, and nothing found, should not onely turne to the generall scandall of the King and the State, as being so suspicious of euery light and friuolous toy, but likewise lay an ill fauoured imputation vpon the Earle of <hi>Northumberland</hi> one of his Maiesties grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Subiects and Counsailors, this <hi>Thomas Percy</hi> being his kinsman and most confident familiar. And the rather were they curious vpon this point, knowing how farre the King detested to be thought suspicious or iealous of any of his good Subiects, though of the meanest degree. And therfore though they all agreed vpon the maine ground, which was to prouide for the securitie of the Kings person, yet did they much differ in the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances,
<pb facs="tcp:135824:27"/>by which this action might be best caried with least dinne and occasion of slander. But the King himselfe still persisting that there were diuers shrewd appearances, and that a narrow search of those places could preiudge no man that was innocent, he at last plainely resolued them, That either must all the parts of those roumes bee nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly searched, and no possibilitie of danger left vnexamined, or else he and they all must resolue not to meddle in it at all, but plainly to go the next day to the Parliament, and leaue the successe to Fortune, which hee beleeued they would be loth to take vpon their consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences: for in such a case as this, an halfe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was worse then no doing at all. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it was at last concluded,
<note place="margin">Agreed that the search should be vnder colour of seeking for Wardrobe stuffe missed by <hi>Whyneyard.</hi>
               </note> That nothing should bee left vnsearched in those Houses: And yet for the better colour and stay of ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour in case nothing were found, it was thought meet, that vpon a pretence of <hi>Why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neards</hi> missing some of the Kings stuffe or Hangings which he had in keeping, all those roumes should be narrowly ripped for them. And to this purpose was Sir <hi>Thomas Kneuet</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:135824:27"/>(a Gentleman of his Maiesties priuie Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) employed, being a Iustice of Peace in <hi>Westminster,</hi> and one, of whose ancient fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie both the late Queene and our now So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereigne haue had large proofe: who accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the trust committed vnto him, went about the midnight next after, to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment house, accompanied with such a small number as was fit for that errand.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fawx</hi> sound at midnight with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the house.</note> But before his entrie in the house, finding <hi>Thomas Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes</hi> alleadged man standing without the doores, his cloathes and boots on at so dead a time of the night, he resolued to apprehend him, as hee did, and thereafter went forward to the searching of the house, where after he had caused to be ouerturned some of the Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets and Coales, he first found one of the small Barrels of powder, and after all the rest, to the number of thirtie sixe Barrels, great and small: And thereafter searching the fellow, whom hee had taken, found three matches, and all other instruments fit for blowing vp the powder, ready vpon him, which made him instantly confesse his owne guiltinesse, declaring also vnto him, That if he had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened
<pb facs="tcp:135824:28"/>to be within the house when he tooke him, as hee was immediatly before (at the ending of his worke) hee would not haue fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to haue blowen him vp, house and all.</p>
            <p>Thus after Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> had caused the wretch to be surely bound, and well guarded by the company he had brought with him, he himselfe returned backe to the Kings Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and gaue warning of his successe to the Lord Chamberlaine,
<note place="margin">Vpon Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Kneuets</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel warned.</note> and Earle of Salisburie, who immediatly warning the rest of the Councel that lay in the house, as soon as they could get themselues ready, came, with their fellow Counsellers, to the Kings Bed-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, being at that time nere foure of the clocke in the morning. And at the first entrie of the Kings Chamber doore, the Lord Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine, being not any longer able to conceale his ioy for the preuenting of so great a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, told the King in a confused haste, that all was found and discouered, and the Traitor in hands and fast bound.</p>
            <p>Then, order being first taken for sending for the rest of the Counsell that lay in the Towne, The prisoner himselfe was brought
<pb facs="tcp:135824:28"/>into the house, where in respect of the strang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the accident, no man was stayed from the sight or speaking with him. And within a while after, the Counsell did examine him; Who seeming to put on a Romane resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, did both to the Counsell, and to euery o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther person that spake with him that day, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare so constant &amp; setled vpon his grounds, as we all thought wee had found some newe <hi>Mutius Scaeuola</hi> borne in England. For not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the horrour of the Fact, the guilt of his conscience, his suddain surprising, the terrour which should haue beene stroken in him by comming into the presence of so graue a Counsell, and the restlesse and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused questions that euery man all that day did vexe him with; Yet was his countenance so farre from being deiected, as he often smi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in scornefull maner, not onely auowing the Fact, but repenting onely, with the said <hi>Scaeuola,</hi> his failing in the execution thereof, whereof (hee said) the Diuell and not God was the discouerer: Answering quickly to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery mans obiection, scoffing at any idle questions which were propounded vnto him,
<pb facs="tcp:135824:29"/>and iesting with such as hee thought had no authoritie to examine him. All that day could the Counsell get nothing out of him touching his Complices, refusing to answere to any such questions which hee thought might discouer the Plot, and laying all the blame vpon himselfe; Whereunto he said he was mooued onely for Religion and consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence sake, denying the King to be his lawfull Soueraigne, or the Anoynted of God in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect hee was an Hereticke, and giuing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe no other name then <hi>Iohn Iohnson,</hi> seruant to <hi>Thomas Percy.</hi> But the next morning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing caried to the Tower, he did not there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine aboue two or three dayes, being twise or thrife in that space reexamined, and the Racke onely offred and shewed vnto him, when the maske of his Romaine fortitude did visibly begin to weare &amp; slide off his face; And then did he begin to confesse part of the trueth, and thereafter to open the whole matter, as doeth appeare by his depositions immediatly following.</p>
            <div type="confession">
               <pb facs="tcp:135824:29"/>
               <head>THE TRVE COPIE OF THE DECLARA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Guido Fawkes,</hi> taken in the presence of the Counsellers, vvhose names are vnder vvritten.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Confesse, that a practise in generall was first broken vnto me, against his Maiestie for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of the Catholique cause, and not inuented or propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by my selfe. And this was first propounded vnto mee about Easter last was twelue moneth beyond the Seas, in the Lowe Countreys of the <hi>Archdukes</hi> obeisance, by <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Winter,</hi> vvho came thereupon with mee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to England, and there we imparted our purpose to three other Gentlemen more, namely, <hi>Robert Catesby, Thomas Percy,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Wright,</hi> who all
<pb facs="tcp:135824:30"/>fiue consulting together of the meanes how to execute the same, and taking a vow among our selues for secrecie; <hi>Catesby</hi> propounded to haue it performed by Gunpowder, and by making a Myne vnder the vpper House of Parliament: which place wee made choice of the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause Religion hauing beene vniustly suppressed there, it was fittest that Iustice and punishment should be executed there.</p>
               <p>This being resolued amongst vs, <hi>Thomas Percy</hi> hired an House at Westminster for that purpose, neere adioyning to the Parliament House, and there we begun to make our Myne about the 11. of December 1604.</p>
               <p>The fiue that first entred into the worke, were <hi>Thomas Percy, Robert Catesby, Thomas Winter, Iohn Wright,</hi> and my selfe: and soone after wee tooke another vnto vs, <hi>Christopher Wright,</hi> hauing sworne him also, and taken the Sacrament for secrecie.</p>
               <p>When we came to the very foundation of the Wall of the House, which vvas about three yards thicke, and found it a matter of great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie, wee tooke vnto vs another Gentleman, <hi>Robert Winter,</hi> in like maner with oath and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as aforesaid.</p>
               <p>It was about Christmas when we brought our Myne vnto the Wall, and about Candlemas we had wrought the Wall halfe through: And whilest they were in working, I stood as Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell
<pb facs="tcp:135824:30"/>to descrie any man that came neere, whereof I gaue them warning, and so they ceased vntill I gaue notice againe to proceede.</p>
               <p>All vve seuen lay in the House, and had Shot and Povvder, being resolued to die in that place before we shouldyeeld or be taken.</p>
               <p>As they were working vpon the Wall, they heard a rushing in a Cellar of remoouing of Coales, whereupon wee feared wee had beene discouered: and they sent me to go to the Cellar, who finding that the Coales were a selling, and that the Cellar was to bee let, vievving the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie thereof for our purpose, <hi>Percy</hi> went and hired the same for yeerely rent.</p>
               <p>We had before this prouided and brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the House tvventie Barrels of Povvder, which we remooued into the Cellar, and couered the same with Billets and Faggots, which were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for that purpose.</p>
               <p>About Easter, the Parliament being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogued till October next, wee dispersed our selues, and I retired into the Low countreys by aduise and direction of the rest, aswel to acquaint <hi>Owen</hi> with the particulars of the Plot, as also least by my longer stay I might haue grovven suspicious, and so haue come in question.</p>
               <p>In the meane time <hi>Percy</hi> hauing the key of the Cellar, laide in more Povvder and wood into it. I returned about the beginning of September next, and then receiuing the key againe of <hi>Percy,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:135824:31"/>we brought in more Povvder and Billets to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the same againe, and so I went for a time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Countrey till the 30. of October.</p>
               <p>It was further resolued amongst vs, that the same day that this Act should haue beene perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, some other of our Confederates should haue surprised the person of the Lady ELIZA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BETH the Kings eldest daughter, who was kept in Warvvickshire at the Lo. <hi>Haringtons</hi> house, and presently haue Proclaimed her Queene, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a Proiect of a Proclaimation ready for that purpose; wherein we made no mention of alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Religion, nor would haue auovved the deede to bee ours, vntill wee should haue had povver enough to make our partie good, and then we would haue auovved both.</p>
               <p>Concerning Duke CHARLES the Kings se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond sonne, wee had sundry consultations how to seise on his Person. But because we found no meanes how to compasse it (the Duke being kept neere London, where wee had not Forces y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough) we resolued to serue our turne with the Lady ELIZABETH.</p>
               <div type="list">
                  <pb facs="tcp:135824:31"/>
                  <head>¶ The names of other principall persons, that vvere made priuy afterwards to this horrible Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracie.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Euerard Digby knight.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ambrose Rookwood.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Francis Tresham.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Grant.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Robert Keyes.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="list">
                  <head>Commiss.</head>
                  <p>Notingham. Worcester. Suffolke. Deuonshire. Northampton. Salisbury. Marre. Dunbar. Popham.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Edw. Coke. W. Waad.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="confession">
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:135824:32"/>
                  <p>ANd in regard that before this discourse could be readie to goe to the Presse, <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Winter</hi> being apprehended, and brought to the Tower, made a confession in substance agreeing with this former of <hi>Fawkes,</hi> onely larger in some circumstances: I haue thought good to insert the same likewise in this place, for the further cleering of the matter, and greater benefit of the Reader.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="confession">
                  <pb facs="tcp:135824:32"/>
                  <head>Thomas Winters Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, taken the xxiii. of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uember</hi> 1605. <hi>in the presence of</hi> the Councellors, whose names are vnder-written.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My most Honorable Lords,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot out of hope to obtaine par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don: for, speaking of my tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall part, I may say, The fault is greater then can be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen; nor affecting hereby the title of a good Subiect: for I must redeeme my Countrey from as great a danger, as I haue hazarded the bringing of Her into, before I can purchase any such opinion; Only at your Honours commaund I will briefly set downe mine owne accusation, and how farre I haue proceeded in this businesse; which I shall the faithfullier doe, since I see such courses are not pleasing to Almighty God, and that all, or the most materiall parts haue bene already con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed.</p>
                  <p>I remayned with my brother in the Countrey from Alhallontyde vntill the beginning of Lent, in the yeere of our Lord 1603. the first yeere of
<pb facs="tcp:135824:33"/>the Kings reigne: about which time Master <hi>Catesby</hi> sent thither, intreating mee to come to London, where he and other my friends would be glad to see me. I desired him to excuse me: for I found my selfe not very well disposed; and (which had happened neuer to me before) retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the messenger without my company. Short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I receiued another letter, in any wise to come. At the second summons I presently came vp, and found him with Master <hi>Iohn Wright</hi> at Lambeth, where he brake with mee, how necessary it was not to forsake our Countrey (for he knew I had then a resolution to goe ouer) but to deliuer her from the seruitude in which she remayned, or at least to assist her with our vttermost endeuours. I answered, That I had often hazarded my life vpon farre lighter termes, and now would not refuse any good occasion, wherein I might doe seruice to the Catholicke cause; but for my selfe I knew no meane probable to succeede. He said that hee had bethought him of a way at one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant to deliuer vs from all our Bonds, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any forraine helpe to replant againe the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Religion; and withal told me in a word, It was to blowe vp the Parliament house with Gunpowder; for, said he, in that place haue they done vs all the mischiefe, and perchance God hath desseigned that place for their punishment. I wondered at the strangenesse of the conceipt, and told him that true it was, this strake at the
<pb facs="tcp:135824:33"/>Roote, and would breed a confusion fit to beget new alterations; But if it should not take effect (as most of this nature miscaryed) the scandall would bee so great which Catholicke Religion might hereby sustaine, as not only our Enemies, but our Friendes also would with good reason condemne vs. He told mee, The nature of the disease required so sharpe a remedie, and asked me if I would giue my consent. I told him, yes, in this or what els soeuer, if he resolued vpon it, I would venture my life. But I proposed many difficulties, As want of an House, and of one to cary the Myne, noyse in the working, and such like. His answere was, Let vs giue an attempt, and where it faileth, passe no further. But first, quoth he, Because wee will leaue no peaceable and quiet way vntryed, you shall goe ouer, and informe the Constable of the state of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes here in England, intreating him to sollicite his Maiestie at his comming hither, that the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Lawes may be recalled, and we admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the rancke of his other Subiects; withall, you may bring ouer some confident Gentleman, such as you shall vnderstand best able for this busines, and named vnto me M. <hi>Fawkes.</hi> Shortly after, I passed the Sea, and found the Constable at <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> neere <hi>Dunkirke,</hi> where, by helpe of M. <hi>Owen</hi> I deliuered my message, Whose answere was that he had strict command from his Master, to do all good Offices for the Catholicks, &amp; for his owne
<pb facs="tcp:135824:34"/>part he thought himselfe bound in conscience so to do, and that no good occasion should be omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but spake to him nothing of this matter.</p>
                  <p>Returning to <hi>Dunkirck</hi> with M. <hi>Owen,</hi> we had speach whether he thought the Constable would faithfully helpe vs, or no. hee sayd he beleeued nothing lesse, and that they sought onely their owne endes, holding small account of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes. I told him that there were many Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in <hi>England,</hi> who would not forsake their Countrey vntill they had tried the vttermost, and rather venture their liues, then forsake her in this miserie. And to adde one more to our number, as a fit man both for counsell and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of whatsoeuer we should resolue, wished for M. <hi>Fawkes,</hi> whome I had heard good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of: he told me the Gentleman deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued no lesse, but was at <hi>Brussels,</hi> and that if hee came not, as happily he might, before my depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, he would send him shortly after into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> I went soone after to <hi>Ostend,</hi> where Sir <hi>William Stanley</hi> as then was not, but came two dayes after. I remained with him three or foure dayes, in which time I asked him, if the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes in <hi>England</hi> should doe any thing to helpe themselues, whether he thought the Archduke Would second them? Hee answered, No, for all those parts were so desirous of peace with <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as they would endure no speach of other en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprise: neither were it fit, sayd hee, to set any
<pb facs="tcp:135824:34"/>proiect afoote now the Peace is vpon conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. I told him there was no such resolution, and so fell to discourse of other matters, vntill I came to speake of M. <hi>Fawkes,</hi> whose company I wished ouer into <hi>England.</hi> I asked of his suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie in the warres, and told him we should need such as hee if occasion required; hee gaue very good commendations of him. And as we were thus discoursing, and I ready to depart for <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,</hi> and taking my leaue of Sir <hi>William,</hi> Master <hi>Fawkes</hi> came into our company, newly returned, and saluted vs. This is the Gentleman, sayd Sir <hi>William,</hi> that you wished for, and so we embraced againe. I told him some good friends of his wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed his company in <hi>England,</hi> and that if he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to come to <hi>Dunkirck,</hi> we would haue further conference, whither I was then going: so taking my leaue of them both, I departed. About two dayes after came M. <hi>Fawkes</hi> to <hi>Dunkirck,</hi> where I told him that wee were vpon a resolution to doe somewhat in <hi>England,</hi> if the Peace with <hi>Spaine</hi> helped vs not, but had as yet resolued vpon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; such or the like talke we passed at <hi>Graue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> where I lay for a winde, and when it serued came both in one Passage to <hi>Greenwich,</hi> neere which place we tooke a paire of Oares, and so came vp to <hi>London,</hi> and came to M. <hi>Catesby</hi> whom we found in his lodging; he welcommed vs into <hi>England,</hi> &amp; asked me what newes from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable. I told him, good words, but I feared the
<pb facs="tcp:135824:35"/>deedes would not answere. This was the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Easter Terme and about the middest of the same Terme, (whether sent for by Master <hi>Catesby,</hi> or vpon some businesse of his owne) vp came M. <hi>Thomas Percy.</hi> The first word he spake (after he came into our company) was, Shall we alwayes (Gentlemen) talke, and neuer doe any thing? M. <hi>Catesby</hi> tooke him aside, and had speach about somewhat to be done, so as first we might all take an oath of secrecy, which wee resolued vvithin tvvo or three daies to do: so as there vve met behind S. <hi>Clements,</hi> M. <hi>Catesby,</hi> M. <hi>Percy,</hi> M. <hi>Wright,</hi> M. <hi>Guy Fawkes,</hi> and my selfe; and hauing vpon a Primer giuen each other the oath of secrecy, in a chamber vvhere no other bodie vvas, vvee vvent after into the next roome and heard Masse, and receiued the blessed Sacrament vpon the same. Then did M. <hi>Catesby</hi> disclose to M. <hi>Percy,</hi> and I together vvith <hi>Iack Wright,</hi> tell to M. <hi>Fawkes</hi> the businesse for vvhich vvee tooke this oath, which they both approued. And then was M. <hi>Percy</hi> sent to take the house, vvhich M. <hi>Catesby</hi> in mine absence had learned did belong to one <hi>Ferris,</hi> which with some difficultie in the end he obtained, &amp; became as <hi>Ferris</hi> before was, Tenant to <hi>Whynniard.</hi> M. <hi>Fawhes</hi> vnderwent the name of M. <hi>Percies</hi> man, calling himselfe <hi>Iohnson,</hi> because his face was the most vnknowen, and receiued the keyes of the house, vntill wee heard that the Parliament was adiorned to the seuenth
<pb facs="tcp:135824:35"/>of February. At which time we all departed se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall wayes into the countrey, to meete againe at the beginning of Michaelmas Terme. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this time also it was thought conuenient to haue a house that might answere to M. <hi>Percies,</hi> where we might make prouision of powder and wood for the Mine, which being there made rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, should in a night bee conueyed by boate to the house by the Parliament, because we were loath to foyle that vvith often going in and out. There was none that wee could deuise so fit as <hi>Lambeth,</hi> where M. <hi>Catesby</hi> often lay, and to bee keeper thereof (by M. <hi>Catesbies</hi> choice) we recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into the number, <hi>Keyes,</hi> as a trusty honest man: this was about a month before <hi>Michaelmas.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Some fortnight after towards the beginning of the Terme, M. <hi>Fawkes</hi> and I came to M. <hi>Cates<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> at <hi>Morecrofts,</hi> vvhere vve agreed that now vvas time to beginne and set things in order for the Mine. So as M. <hi>Fawkes</hi> went to <hi>London,</hi> and the next day sent for me to come ouer to him: when I came, the cause was, for that the Scottish Lords were appointed to sit in conference of the Vnion in M. <hi>Percies</hi> house. This hindered our beginning vntill a fortnight before Christmas, by vvhich time both Master <hi>Percy</hi> and M. <hi>Wright</hi> were come to <hi>London,</hi> and vve against their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming had prouided a good part of the powder: so as vve all fiue entred with tooles fit to begin our worke, hauing prouided our selues of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked-meates,
<pb facs="tcp:135824:36"/>the lesse to need sending abroad. We entred late in the night, and were neuer seene saue only M. <hi>Percyes</hi> man, vntill Christmas Eue. In which time vve wrought vnder a little Entry to the wall of the Parliament house, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propped it, as we vvent, vvith vvood.</p>
                  <p>Whilest we were together, we began to fashi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our businesse, and discoursed what we should doe after this deed was done. The first question vvas how vve might surprise the next heire, the Prince haply vvould be at the Parliament vvith the King his Father, how should we then be able to sease on the Duke? This burthen M. <hi>Percy</hi> vndertooke, that by his acquaintance, hee, vvith another Gentleman would enter the Chamber without suspicion, &amp; hauing some dozen others at seuerall doores to expect his comming, and two or three on horsebacke at the Court gate to receiue him, he vvould vndertake (the blow being giuen, vntill vvhich hee vvould attend in the Dukes Chamber) to carry him safe avvay: for he supposed most of the Court vvould be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, and such as vvere there not suspecting, or vnprouided for any such matter. For the Lady ELIZABETH, it vvere easie to surprise her in the countrey by dravving friends together at an hunting neere the Lord <hi>Haringtons,</hi> and Ashby, M. <hi>Catesbyes</hi> house, being not farre off vvas a fit place for preparation.</p>
                  <p>The next vvas for mony and horses, vvhich if
<pb facs="tcp:135824:36"/>we could prouide in any reasonable measure (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the Heire apparant) &amp; the first knovvledge by foure or fiue dayes, vvas oddes sufficient.</p>
                  <p>Then vvhat Lords vve should saue from the Parliament, vvhich vvas first agreed in generall as many as we could that were Catholickes, or so disposed: But after we descended to speake of particulars.</p>
                  <p>Next what forreine Princes wee should ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint vvith this before, or ioyne with after. For this point we agreed, that first vve could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne Princes to that secrecie, nor oblige them by oath, so to be secure of their promise: besides vve knew not whether they wil approue the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect or dislike it. And if they doe allow thereof, to prepare before might beget suspicion; and not to prouide vntill the businesse vvere acted, the same letter that caried newes of the thing done, might as vvell intreate their helpe and furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. <hi>Spaine</hi> is too slow in his preparations to hope any good from in the first extremities, and <hi>France</hi> too neere and too dangerous, vvho with the shipping of <hi>Holland,</hi> we feared of all the world might make away with vs.</p>
                  <p>But vvhile we vvere in the middle of these dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses, we heard that the Parliament should be anew adiourned vntill after Michaelmas, vpon which tidings wee broke off both discourse and vvorking vntill after Christmas. About Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlemas vve brought ouer in a boate the powder,
<pb facs="tcp:135824:37"/>vvhich vvee had prouided at Lambeth, and layd it in M. <hi>Percyes</hi> house, because vve vvere vvilling to haue all our danger in one place.</p>
                  <p>We vvrought also another fortnight in the Myne against the stone wall, vvhich vvas very hard to beate thorow; at vvhich time vve called in <hi>Kit VVright,</hi> and neere to Easter, as vvee vvrought the third time, opportunitie vvas gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to hire the Cellar, in vvhich vve resolued to lay the povvder, and leaue the Myne.</p>
                  <p>Novv by reason that the charge of maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vs all so long together, besides the number of seuerall houses, vvhich for seuerall vses had been hired, and buying of povvder &amp;c. had layne heauie on M. <hi>Catesby</hi> alone to support; it was necessary for him to call in some others to ease his charge, and to that ende desired leaue, that hee, with M. <hi>Percy,</hi> and a third, whom they should call, might acquaint whom they thought fit and willing to the businesse: for many, said he, may be content that I should know, who would not therefore that all the company should be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with their names: to this we all agreed.</p>
                  <p>After this Master <hi>Fawkes</hi> layd into the Cellar (which he had newly taken) a thousand of Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, and fiue hundred of Faggots, and vvith that couered the Powder, because we might haue the House free, to suffer any one to enter that would. M. <hi>Catesby</hi> wished vs to consider, whether it were not novv necessary to send M. <hi>Fawkes</hi> ouer, both
<pb facs="tcp:135824:37"/>to absent himselfe for a time, as also to acquaint Sir <hi>William Stanley</hi> and M. <hi>Owen</hi> vvith this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Wee agreed that he should (prouided that he gaue it them vvith the same othe that vvee had taken it before) <hi>videlicet,</hi> to keepe it secret from all the vvorld. The reason why vve desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Sir <hi>William Stanley</hi> should be acquainted here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvith vvas, to haue him vvith vs so soone as hee could: And for M. <hi>Owen,</hi> hee might hold good correspondencie after vvith forraine Princes. So M. <hi>Fawkes</hi> departed about Easter for <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> and returned the later end of August. Hee told me that vvhen he arriued at <hi>Brussels,</hi> Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Stanley</hi> vvas not returned from <hi>Spaine,</hi> so as he vttered the matter onely to <hi>Owen,</hi> who see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vvell pleased vvith the businesse, but told him that surely Sir <hi>William</hi> would not bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with any plot, as hauing businesse now afoot in the Court of <hi>England:</hi> but hee himselfe would be alvvayes ready to tell it him, and send him avvay so soone as it were done.</p>
                  <p>About this time did M. <hi>Percy</hi> and M. <hi>Catesby</hi> meet at the <hi>Bathe,</hi> where they agreed that the company being yet but few, M. <hi>Catesby</hi> should haue the others authoritie to call in whom hee thought best; By which authoritie he called in after, Sir <hi>Euerard Digby,</hi> though at what time I know not, and last of all Master <hi>Francis Tresham.</hi> The first promised, as I heard M. <hi>Catesby</hi> say, fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene hundred pounds; The second two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand
<pb facs="tcp:135824:38"/>pounds; M. <hi>Percy</hi> himselfe promised all that hee could get of the Earle of <hi>Northumberlands</hi> rents, which was about foure thousand pounds, and to prouide many galloping horses to the number of ten.</p>
                  <p>Meane while M. <hi>Fawkes</hi> and my selfe alone bought some new Powder, as suspecting the first to be danke, and conueyed it into the Cellar, and set it in order, as vvee resolued it should stand. Then was the Parliament anew prorogued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the fift of Nouember, so as vve all went dovvn vntill some ten dayes before, vvhen M. <hi>Catesby</hi> came vp vvith M. <hi>Fawkes</hi> to an house by <hi>Enfield Chace</hi> called <hi>White-webbes,</hi> whither I came to them, and M. <hi>Catesby</hi> willed mee to enquire whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the yong Prince came to the Parliament: I told him that I heard that his Grace thought not to be there. Then must we haue our Horses said M <hi>Catesby</hi> beyond the vvater, and prouision of more company to surprise the Prince, and leaue the Duke alone.</p>
                  <p>Two dayes after being Sunday at night, in came one to my chamber, and told me that a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter had bene giuen to my L. <hi>Mountegle</hi> to this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, That he vvished his Lordships absence from the Parliament, Because a Blow would there be giuen; Which letter hee presently carried to my L. of <hi>Salisbury.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>On the morrow I went to <hi>White-webbes,</hi> and told it <hi>M. Catesby,</hi> assuring him vvithall that the
<pb facs="tcp:135824:38"/>matter vvas disclosed: and wishing him in any case to forsake his Countrey. Hee told me hee would see further as yet, and resolued to send M. <hi>Fawkes</hi> to trie the vttermost, protesting if the part belonged to himselfe, hee would trie the same aduenture.</p>
                  <p>On Wednesday Master <hi>Fawkes</hi> went and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned at night, of which we were very glad.</p>
                  <p>Thursday I came to London, and Friday Master <hi>Catesby,</hi> Master <hi>Tresham</hi> and I met at <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net,</hi> where we questioned how this Letter should bee sent to my Lord <hi>Mountegle,</hi> but could not conceiue, for Master <hi>Tresham</hi> forsware it, whom we only suspected.</p>
                  <p>On Saturday night I met M. <hi>Tresham</hi> againe in Lincolnes Inne walkes. Wherein he told such speeches, that my L. of <hi>Salisbury</hi> should vse to the King, as I gaue it lost the second time, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated the same to M. <hi>Catesby,</hi> who hereupon was resolued to be gone, but staid to haue Master <hi>Percy</hi> come vp, whose consent herein we wanted. On Sunday M. <hi>Percy</hi> being dealt with to that end, would needs abide the vttermost triall.</p>
                  <p>This suspicion of all hands put vs into such confusion, as Master <hi>Catesby</hi> resolued to goe dovvn into the Countrey the Munday that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>Percy</hi> went to Syon, and Master <hi>Percy</hi> resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to follow the same night, or earely the next morning. About fiue of the clocke being Tues<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, came the yonger <hi>Wright</hi> to my Chamber,
<pb facs="tcp:135824:39"/>and told me that a Nobleman called the Lord <hi>Mounteagle,</hi> saying, Arise, and come along to <hi>Essex</hi> house, for I am going to call vp my Lord of <hi>Northumberland:</hi> saying withall, The matter is discouered. Goe backe Master <hi>Wright</hi> (quoth I) and learne what you can about <hi>Essex</hi> gate. Shortly hee returned and said, Surely all is lost: for <hi>Lepton</hi> is got on horsebacke at <hi>Essex</hi> doore, and as hee parted, hee asked if their Lordships would haue any more with him: and being an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>svvered No, is rode fast vp Fleetstreete as he can ride. Goe you then (quoth I) to M. <hi>Percy,</hi> for sure it is for him they seeke, and bid him be gone, I will stay and see the vttermost. Then I went to the Court gates and found them straightly garded, so as no body could enter. From thence I went dovvne towards the Parliament house, and in the middle of Kings streete, found the Garde standing that would not let me passe. And as I returned I heard one say, There is a Treason discouered, in which the King and the Lords should haue beene blovven vp. So then I was fully satisfied that all was knowen, and went to the Stable where my Gelding stoode, and rode into the Countrey. M. <hi>Catesby</hi> had appointed our meeting at <hi>Dunchurch,</hi> but I could not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them vntill I came to my brothers, which was Wednesday night. On Thursday we tooke the Armour at my L. <hi>Windsores,</hi> and went that night to one <hi>Stephen Littletons</hi> house, where the
<pb facs="tcp:135824:39"/>next day (being Friday) as I was early abroad to discouer, my man came to me, and said, that an heauie mischance had seuered all the companie, for that M. <hi>Catesby,</hi> M. <hi>Rookwood,</hi> and M. <hi>Grant,</hi> vvere burned vvith Gunpovvder, vpon vvhich sight the rest dispersed. Master <hi>Littleton</hi> vvished me to flie, and so vvould he. I told him I vvould first see the body of my friend and burie him, vvhatsoeuer befel me. When I came, I found M. <hi>Catesby</hi> reasonable vvell, Master <hi>Percy,</hi> both the <hi>Wrights,</hi> M. <hi>Rookwood,</hi> and Master <hi>Grant.</hi> I asked them vvhat they resolued to do: they ansvvered, We meane here to die. I said againe, I vvould take such part as they did. About eleuen of the clock came the companie to beset the house, and as I walked into the court, I was shot into the shoulder, which lost me the vse of mine arme: the next shot was the elder <hi>Wright</hi> stricken dead, after him the yonger M. <hi>Wright,</hi> &amp; fourthly <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brose Rookwood</hi> shot. Then said M. <hi>Catesby</hi> to me (standing before the doore they were to enter) Stand by me <hi>Tom,</hi> and we will die together. Sir (quoth I) I haue lost the vse of my right arme, and I feare that will cause me to be taken. So as vve stoode close together, M. <hi>Catesby,</hi> M. <hi>Percy,</hi> and my selfe, they tvvo vvere shot (as farre as I could guesse vvith one Bullet) and then the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie entered vpon me, hurt mee in the Belly vvith a Pike, and gaue me other vvounds, vntill
<pb facs="tcp:135824:40"/>one came behind, and caught holde of both mine armes.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>And so I remaine yours, &amp;c.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="list">
                  <head>Commiss.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Notingham, Suffolk, Worcester, Deuonshire, Northampton, Salisbury, Marr, Dunbar, Popham.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Edw. Coke. W. Waad.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="list">
                  <head>¶ <hi>The names of those that were</hi> first in the Treason, and laboured in the Myne.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>Robert Catesby. Esquires.</item>
                     <item>Robert Winter. Esquires.</item>
                     <item>Thomas Percy. Gentlemen.</item>
                     <item>Thomas Winter. Gentlemen.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Wright. Gentlemen.</item>
                     <item>Christopher Wright. Gentlemen.</item>
                     <item>Guido Favvkes. Gentlemen.</item>
                     <item>And Bates Catesbies man.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="list">
                  <pb facs="tcp:135824:40"/>
                  <head>¶ <hi>Those that were made acquainted</hi> with it, though not personally la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring in the Myne, nor in the Cellar.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>Euerard Digby. Knight.</item>
                     <item>Ambrose Rookvvood. Esquires.</item>
                     <item>Francis Tresham. Esquires.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Graunt. Gent.</item>
                     <item>Robert Keyes.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>BVt here let vs leaue <hi>Fawkes</hi> in a lodging fit for such a guest, and taking time to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise vpon his conscience; and turne our selues to that part of the Historie, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes the fortune of the rest of his parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers in that abominable Treason. The newes was no sooner spred abroad that morning, which was vpon a Tuesday, the fift of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uember,</hi> and the first day designed for that Session of Parliament; The newes (I say) of this so strange and vnlooked for accident was no sooner diuulged, but some of those Conspiratours, namely <hi>Winter,</hi> and the two
<pb facs="tcp:135824:41"/>brothers of <hi>VVrights</hi> thought it high time for them to hasten out of the Towne (for <hi>Catesby</hi> was gone the night before, and <hi>Percy</hi> at foure of the clocke in the morning the same day of the Discouerie) and all of them helde their course, with more haste then good speede to <hi>VVarwicke</hi> Shire toward <hi>Couentry,</hi> where the next day morning being <hi>Wednesday,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the same houre that <hi>Fawkes</hi> was taken in <hi>Westminster,</hi> one <hi>Graunt</hi> a Gentleman ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing associated vnto him some others of his opinion, all violent Papists and strong Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sants,
<note place="margin">The taking of the horses out of the stable at Warwicke by <hi>Graunt</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> came to a Stable of one <hi>Benocke</hi> a rider of great Horses, and hauing violently broken vp the same, caried along with them all the great Horses that were therein, to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of seuen or eight, belonging to diuers Noblemen and Gentlemen of that Country, who had put them into the Riders hands to be made fit for their seruice. And so both that company of them which fled out of <hi>London,</hi> as also <hi>Graunt</hi> and his complices met all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at <hi>Dunchurch</hi> at Sir <hi>Euerard Digby</hi> his lodging the Tuesday at night, after the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerie of this treacherous Attempt: The
<pb facs="tcp:135824:41"/>which <hi>Digby</hi> had likewise for his part appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a match of hunting to haue bene hunted the next day, which was Wednesday,
<note place="margin">The hunting match appointed by Sir <hi>Euerard Digby.</hi>
                  </note> though his mind was <hi>Nimrod</hi>-like vpon a farre other maner of hunting, more bent vpon the blood of reasonable men then bruite beasts.</p>
               <p>This companie and hellish societie thus conuened, finding their purpose discouered,
<note place="margin">Their going into armes after the Plot discouered.</note> and their treacherie preuented, did resolue to run a desperate course, and since they could not preuaile by so priuate a Blow, to practise by a publike Rebellion either to attaine to their Intents, or at least to saue themselues in the throng of others. And therefore gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all the company they could vnto them, and pretending the quarrell of Religion, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing intercepted such prouision of Armour, Horses, and Powder, as the time could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, thought by running vp and downe the Countrey both to augment peece and peece their number (dreaming to themselues that they had the vertue of a Snow-ball, which being little at the first, and tumbling downe from a great hill groweth to a great quantity, by encreasing it selfe with the Snow that it
<pb facs="tcp:135824:42"/>meeteth by the way) and also that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning first this braue shewe in one part of the countrey, should by their Sympathy and example stirre vp and encourage the rest of their Religion in other parts of <hi>England</hi> to rise, as they had done there. But when they had gathered their force to the greatest, they came not to the number of fourescore,
<note place="margin">Their number neuer aboue foure score.</note> &amp; yet were they troubled all the houres of the day to keepe and containe their owne seruants from stealing from them; who (notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of all their care) dayly left them, being farre inferior to <hi>Gedeons</hi> hoste in number, but farre more in faith or iustnesse of quarell.</p>
               <p>And so after that this Catholicke troupe had wandered a while through <hi>Warwicke</hi> shire to <hi>Worcester</hi> shire, and from thence to the edge and borders of <hi>Stafford</hi> shire, this gallantly armed band had not the honour at the last to be beaten with a Kings Lieutenant or extraordinary Commissioner sent downe for the purpose, but onely by the ordinary Shiriffe of <hi>Worcester</hi> shire were they all bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,
<note place="margin">Their flight.</note> killed, taken and dispersed. Wherein ye haue to note this following circumstance so
<pb facs="tcp:135824:42"/>admirable, and so viuely displaying the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of Gods iustice, as it could not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed without betraying in a maner the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry due to the Almightie for the same.</p>
               <p>Although diuers of the Kings Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were posted downe after these Traitors with all the speede possible, declaring the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diousnesse of that bloody attempt, the neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie to haue had <hi>Percy</hi> preserued aliue, if it had been possible, and the assembly together of that rightly damned crew, now no more darned Conspirators, but open and auowed Rebels: yet the far distance of the way (which was aboue an hundred miles) together with the extreme deepenesse thereof, ioyned also with the shortnesse of the day, was the cause that the heartie and louing affections of the Kings good Subiects in those parts preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the speed of his Proclamations. For vpon the third day after the flying downe of these Rebels, which was vpon the Friday next after the discouerie of their Plot,
<note place="margin">Ouertaken at <hi>Holbeach</hi> in Stafford shire, <hi>Stephen Lattle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> house.</note> they were most of them all surprized by the Shiriffe of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester</hi> shire at <hi>Holbeach,</hi> about the noone of the day, and that in manner following.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:135824:43"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Graunt,</hi> of whom I haue made mention be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for taking the great horses, who had not all the preceding time stirred from his owne house till the next morning after the attempt should haue beene put in execution, he then laying his accompt without his Host (as the prouerbe is) that their Plot had, without fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, receiued the day before their hoped for successe; Tooke, or rather stole out those hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses (as I said before) for enabling him, and so many of that soulesse societie that had stil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in the Countrey neere about him, to make a sudden surprise vpon the Kings elder daughter,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Grants</hi> attempt to surprise the Lady <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
                  </note> the Lady ELIZABETH, hauing her residence nere by that place, whom they thought to haue vsed for the colour of their treacherous dessigne (His Maiestie her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, her mother, and male children being all destroyed aboue.) And to this purpose also had that <hi>Nimrod Digby,</hi> prouided his hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting march against that same time, that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of people being flocked together vpon the pretence thereof, they might the easilier haue brought to passe the sudden surprise of her person.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:135824:43"/>
               <p>Now the violent taking away of those hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses long before day, did seeme to be so great aryot in the eyes of the Common people, that knewe of no greater mystery: And the bold attempting thereof did ingender such a suspicion of some following Rebellion in the hearts of the wiser sort, as both great and small began to stirre and arme themselues, vpon this vnlooked for accident. Among whom Sir <hi>Fulke Greuill</hi> the elder, Knight, as became one both so ancient in yeeres and good reputation, and by his Office being Deputie Lieutenant of Warwicke-shire, though vnhable in his body, yet by the zeale and true feruencie of his minde, did first ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend this foresaid Riot to be nothing but the sparkles and sure <hi>indices</hi> of a following Rebellion; whereupon both stoutly and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly hee tooke order to get into his owne hands, the Munition and Armor of all such Gentlemen about him, as were either absent from their owne houses, or in doubtfull guard; And also sent such direction to the Townes about him, as thereupon did follow the striking of <hi>Winter</hi> by a poore Smith, who
<pb facs="tcp:135824:44"/>had likewise bene taken by those vulgar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but that he was rescued by the rest of his company, who perceiuing that the Countrey before them had notice of them, hastened a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with losse in their owne sight, Sixteene of their folowers being taken by the Townes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and sent presently to the Sheriffe at Warwicke, and from thence to London.</p>
               <p>But before twelue or sixteene houres past, <hi>Catesby, Percy,</hi> the <hi>Winters, Wrights, Rooke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> and the rest bringing then the assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that their maine Plot was failed and bewrayed, whereupon they had builded the golden mountaines of their glorious hopes: They then tooke their last desperate resolution to flocke together in a troupe, &amp; wander, as they did, for the reasons afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told. But as vpon the one part, the zealous duety to their God and their Souereigne was so deepely imprinted in the hearts of all the meanest and poorest sort of the people (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though then knowing of no further myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie then such publike misbehauiours, as their owne eyes taught them) as notwithstanding of their faire shewes and pretence of their
<pb facs="tcp:135824:44"/>Catholicke cause, no creature, man or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man through all the Countrey, would once so much as giue them willingly a cup of drinke, or any sort of comfort or support, but with execrations detested them: So on the other part, the Shiriffes of the Shires, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>through they wandered, conuening their people with all speede possible, hunted as hotly after them, as the euilnesse of the way, and the vnprouidednesse of their people vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that sudden could permit them. And so at last after Sir <hi>Richard Verney,</hi> Shiriffe of <hi>Warwicke</hi> shire, had carefully and straightly beene in chase of them to the confines of his Countie, part of the meaner sort being also apprehended by him: Sir <hi>Richard Walsh</hi> Shiriffe of <hi>Worcester</hi> shire did likewise dueti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and hotly pursue them thorowe his Shire; And hauing gotten sure tryall of their taking harbour at the house abouenamed, hee did send Trumpetters and Messengers to them, commaunding them in the Kings name to render vnto him, his Maiesties mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister; and knowing no more at that time of their guilt then was publikely visible,
<pb facs="tcp:135824:45"/>did promise vpon their duetifull and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent rendring vnto him, to intercede at the Kings handes for the sparing of their liues: Who receiued onely from them this scorne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full answere (they being better witnesses to themselues of their inward euill consciences) <hi>That he had neede of better assistance, then of those few numbers that were with him, before he could be able to commaund or comptroll them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But here fel the wonderous worke of Gods Iustice,
<note place="margin">The preparation to assault the house.</note> That while this message passed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Sheriffe and them, The Sheriffes and his peoples zeale being iustly kindled and augmented by their arrogant answere, and so they preparing themselues to giue a furious assault; and the other partie making themselues ready within the house to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme their promise by a defence as resolute; It pleased God that in the mending of the fire in their chamber, one small sparke should flie out, and light among lesse then two pound weight of Powder, which was drying a little from the chimney; which beeing thereby blowen vp, so maymed the faces of some of the principal Rebels, and the hands and sides
<pb facs="tcp:135824:45"/>of others of them (blowing vp with it also a great bag full of Powder, which notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding neuer tooke fire) as they were not onely disabled and discouraged hereby from any further resistance, in respect <hi>Catesby</hi> himselfe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Catesby</hi> who was the first inuentor of this Treason in generall, and of the manner of working the same by powder, in special, himselfe now first maimed with the blowing vp of powder, and next he and <hi>Percy</hi> both killed with one shot procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</note>
                  <hi>Rookwood, Grant,</hi> &amp; diuers others of greatest accompt, among them were thereby made vnable for defence: but also wonderfully stroken with amazement in their guilty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences, calling to memory how God had iustly punished them with that same Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which they should haue vsed for the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuating of so great a sinne, according to the old Latin saying, <hi>In quo peccamus, in eodem plectimur;</hi> as they presently (see the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull power of Gods Iustice vpon guiltie consciences) did all fall downe vpon their knees, praying GOD to pardon them for their bloody enterprize; And thereafter gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ouer any further debate, opened the gate, suffered the Sheriffes people to rush in fariously among them, &amp; desperately sought their owne present destruction; The three specials of them ioyning backs together, <hi>Catesbie, Percy,</hi> and <hi>Winter,</hi> whereof two
<pb facs="tcp:135824:46"/>with one shot, <hi>Catesby</hi> and <hi>Percy</hi> were slaine, and the third, <hi>Winter,</hi> taken and saued aliue.</p>
               <p>And thus these resolute and high aspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Catholikes, who dreamed of no lesse then the destruction of Kings &amp; kingdomes, and promised to themselues no lower estate then the gouernment of great and ancient Monarchies; were miserably defeated, and quite ouerthrowne in an instant, falling in the pit which they had prepared for others; and so fulfilling that sentence which his Maiestie did in a manner prophecie of them in his Oration to the Parliament: some pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently slaine, others deadly wounded, strip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped of their clothes, left lying miserably na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and so dying rather of colde, then of the danger of their wounds; and the rest that either were whole, or but lightly hurt, taken and led prisoners by the Sheriffe the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie minister of Iustice, to the Gaole, the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie place euen of the basest malefactors, where they remained till their sending vp to London, beeing met with a huge conflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of people of all sorts, desirous to see them as the rarest sort of Monsters; fooles to
<pb facs="tcp:135824:46"/>laugh at them, women and children to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, all the common people to gaze, the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser sort to satisfie their curiositie in seeing the outward cases of so vnheard of a villany: and generally all sorts of people to satiate and fill their eyes with the sight of them, whom in their hearts they so farre admired and dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted: Seruing so for a fearefull and publike spectacle of Gods fierce wrath and iust indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
               <p>What hereafter will be done with them, is to be left to the Iustice of his Maiesty and the State. Which as no good Subiect needes to doubt will bee performed in the owne due time by a publike and an exemplarie punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: So haue wee all that are faithfull and humble subiects, great cause to pray earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Almightie, that it wil please him who hath the hearts of all Princes in his hands, to put it in his Maiesties heart to make such a conclusion of this Tragedie to the Traytors, but tragicomedie to the King and all his true Subiects; as thereby the glory of God and his true Religion may bee aduanced, the future securitie of the King and his estate procured
<pb facs="tcp:135824:47"/>and prouided for, all hollow and vnhonest hearts discouered and preuented, and this horrible attempt (lacking due epithites) to bee so iustly auenged, That where they thought by one Catholike indeed, and Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall blowe to accomplish the wish of that Romane Tyrant, who wished all the bodies in Rome to haue but one necke, and so by the violent force of Powder to breake vp as with a Pettard our triple locked peacefull gates of <hi>Ianus,</hi> which (God be thanked) they could not compasse by any other meanes; they may iustly bee so recompensed for their truely viperous intended Parricide,
<note place="margin">As <hi>Aeneas Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius</hi> doth nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly write con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of King <hi>Iames</hi> the first of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the following punishment of the Traytors, whereof him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe was an eye witnesse. <hi>Hist. de Europa, cap.</hi> 46.</note> as the shame and infamie that otherwise would light vpon this whole Nation, for hauing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunately hatched such Cockatrice egges, may be repaired by the execution of famous and honourable iustice vpon the offendours, and so the Kingdome purged of them, may hereafter perpetually flourish in peace and prosperitie, by the happie coniunction of the hearts of all honest and true Subiects, with their iust and religious Soueraigne.</p>
               <p>And thus whereas they thought to haue
<pb facs="tcp:135824:47"/>effaced our memories, the memorie of them shall remaine (but to their perpetuall infamy) and we (as I said in the beginning) shall with all thankfulnesse eternally preserue the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of so great a benefit. To which let euery good subiect say</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:135824:48"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:135824:48"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>